Hi. My name is Marwa. and I'm an architect.
[AI] 你好我叫玛瓦。我是一名建筑师。
I was born and raised in Homs.
[AI] 我在霍姆斯出生和长大。
a city in the central western part of Syria.
[AI] 叙利亚中西部一城市。
and I've always lived here.
[AI] 我一直住在这里。
After six years of war.
[AI] 经过六年的战争。
Homs is now a half-destroyed city.
[AI] 霍姆斯现在是一座被摧毁了一半的城市。
My family and I were lucky; our place is still standing.
[AI] 我的家人和我都很幸运；我们的地方仍然存在。
Although for two years. we were like prisoners at home.
[AI] 虽然已经有两年了。我们就像家里的囚犯。
Outside there were demonstrations and battles and bombings and snipers.
[AI] 外面有示威、战斗、爆炸和狙击手。
My husband and I used to run an architecture studio
[AI] 我丈夫和我曾经经营一家建筑工作室
in the old town main square.
[AI] 在老城主广场。
It's gone. as is most of the old town itself.
[AI] 它不见了。老城区的大部分地区也是如此。
Half of the city's other neighborhoods
[AI] 该市其他社区的一半
are now rubble.
[AI] 现在是废墟。
Since the ceasefire in late 2015.
[AI] 自2015年末停火以来。
large parts of Homs have been more or less quiet.
[AI] 霍姆斯的大部分地区或多或少都很安静。
The economy is completely broken. and people are still fighting.
[AI] 经济完全崩溃了。人们还在战斗。
The merchants who had stalls in the old city market
[AI] 旧城市场上有摊位的商人
now trade out of sheds on the streets.
[AI] 现在在街上的棚子里交易。
Under our apartment. there is a carpenter.
[AI] 在我们的公寓下面。有一个木匠。
sweetshops. a butcher. a printing house. workshops. among many more.
[AI] 糖果店。屠夫。印刷厂。讲习班。还有很多。
I have started teaching part-time.
[AI] 我开始兼职教书。
and with my husband. who juggles several jobs.
[AI] 还有我丈夫。他兼好几份工作。
we've opened a small bookshop.
[AI] 我们开了一家小书店。
Other people do all sorts of jobs to get by.
[AI] 其他人做各种各样的工作来维持生计。
When I look at my destroyed city. of course. I ask myself:
[AI] 当我看着我被摧毁的城市。当然我问自己：
What has led to this senseless war?
[AI] 是什么导致了这场毫无意义的战争？
Syria was largely a place of tolerance.
[AI] 叙利亚在很大程度上是一个宽容的地方。
historically accustomed to variety.
[AI] 历史上习惯于多样性。
accommodating a wide range of beliefs. origins. customs.
[AI] 适应广泛的信仰。起源。海关
goods. food.
[AI] 商品食物
How did my country --
[AI] 我的国家怎么样--
a country with communities living harmoniously together
[AI] 社区和谐共处的国家
and comfortable in discussing their differences --
[AI] 并且乐于讨论他们的分歧--
how did it degenerate into civil war. violence. displacement
[AI] 它是如何演变成内战的。暴力取代
and unprecedented sectarian hatred?
[AI] 以及前所未有的宗派仇恨？
There were many reasons that had led to the war --
[AI] 导致这场战争的原因有很多--
social. political and economic.
[AI] 社会的政治和经济。
They all have played their role.
[AI] 他们都发挥了自己的作用。
But I believe there is one key reason that has been overlooked
[AI] 但我相信有一个被忽视的关键原因
and which is important to analyze.
[AI] 这对分析很重要。
because from it will largely depend
[AI] 因为这在很大程度上取决于
whether we can make sure that this doesn't happen again.
[AI] 我们是否能确保这种情况不再发生。
And that reason is architecture.
[AI] 这就是建筑的原因。
Architecture in my country has played an important role
[AI] 建筑在我国发挥了重要作用
in creating. directing and amplifying conflict between warring factions.
[AI] 在创造中。指挥和扩大交战派系之间的冲突。
and this is probably true for other countries as well.
[AI] 其他国家也可能如此。
There is a sure correspondence between the architecture of a place
[AI] 一个地方的建筑结构之间有着必然的对应关系
and the character of the community that has settled there.
[AI] 以及定居在那里的社区的特征。
Architecture plays a key role in whether a community crumbles
[AI] 建筑在社区是否崩溃中起着关键作用
or comes together.
[AI] 或者走到一起。
Syrian society has long lived the coexistence
[AI] 叙利亚社会长期共存
of different traditions and backgrounds.
[AI] 具有不同的传统和背景。
Syrians have experienced the prosperity of open trade
[AI] 叙利亚人经历了开放贸易的繁荣
and sustainable communities.
[AI] 和可持续社区。
They have enjoyed the true meaning of belonging to a place.
[AI] 他们享受到了属于一个地方的真正意义。
and that was reflected in their built environment.
[AI] 这反映在他们的建筑环境中。
in the mosques and churches built back-to-back.
[AI] 在连续建造的清真寺和教堂里。
in the interwoven souks and public venues.
[AI] 在交织的露天市场和公共场所。
and the proportions and sizes based on principles of humanity and harmony.
[AI] 以及基于人性和和谐原则的比例和大小。
This architecture of mixity can still be read in the remains.
[AI] 这种混合性的结构仍然可以在遗骸中看到。
The old Islamic city in Syria was built over a multilayered past.
[AI] 叙利亚古老的伊斯兰城市是在多层次的历史基础上建成的。
integrating with it and embracing its spirit.
[AI] 融入它，拥抱它的精神。
So did its communities.
[AI] 它的社区也是如此。
People lived and worked with each other
[AI] 人们生活和工作在一起
in a place that gave them a sense of belonging
[AI] 在一个让他们有归属感的地方
and made them feel at home.
[AI] 让他们有宾至如归的感觉。
They shared a remarkably unified existence.
[AI] 他们有着非常统一的生活。
But over the last century.
[AI] 但是在过去的一个世纪里。
gradually this delicate balance of these places has been interfered with;
[AI] 这些地方的微妙平衡逐渐受到干扰；
first. by the urban planners of the colonial period.
[AI] 第一由殖民地时期的城市规划者设计。
when the French went enthusiastically about.
[AI] 当法国人热情奔走的时候。
transforming what they saw as the un-modern Syrian cities.
[AI] 改变他们眼中的非现代叙利亚城市。
They blew up city streets and relocated monuments.
[AI] 他们炸毁了城市街道，重新安置了纪念碑。
They called them improvements.
[AI] 他们称之为改进。
and they were the beginning of a long. slow unraveling.
[AI] 这是一个漫长历史的开始。慢慢解开。
The traditional urbanism and architecture of our cities
[AI] 我们城市的传统城市主义和建筑
assured identity and belonging not by separation.
[AI] 确保身份和归属，而不是通过分离。
but by intertwining.
[AI] 而是通过缠绕。
But over time. the ancient became worthless. and the new. coveted.
[AI] 但随着时间的推移。古人变得一文不值。还有新的。垂涎三尺。
The harmony of the built environment and social environment
[AI] 建筑环境与社会环境的和谐
got trampled over by elements of modernity --
[AI] 被现代元素践踏了--
brutal. unfinished concrete blocks.
[AI] 残酷的未完工的混凝土砌块。
neglect. aesthetic devastation.
[AI] 疏于照顾审美破坏。
divisive urbanism that zoned communities by class. creed or affluence.
[AI] 按阶级划分社区的分裂城市主义。信条或富裕。
And the same was happening to the community.
[AI] 社区也是如此。
As the shape of the built environment changed.
[AI] 随着建筑环境形状的改变。
so the lifestyles and sense of belonging of the communities
[AI] 因此，社区的生活方式和归属感
also started changing.
[AI] 也开始改变。
From a register of togetherness. of belonging.
[AI] 从一个团结的记录。归属感。
architecture became a way of differentiation.
[AI] 建筑成为一种差异化的方式。
and communities started drifting apart
[AI] 社区开始疏远
from the very fabric that used to unite them.
[AI] 从曾经使他们团结在一起的织物上。
and from the soul of the place that used to represent their common existence.
[AI] 来自这个曾经代表他们共同存在的地方的灵魂。
While many reasons had led to the Syrian war.
[AI] 叙利亚战争的原因很多。
we shouldn't underestimate the way in which.
[AI] 我们不应该低估这一点。
by contributing to the loss  of identity and self-respect.
[AI] 导致身份和自尊的丧失。
urban zoning and misguided. inhumane architecture
[AI] 城市分区和误导。非人性建筑
have nurtured sectarian divisions and hatred.
[AI] 助长了宗派分裂和仇恨。
Over time. the united city has morphed into a city center
[AI] 随着时间的推移。联合城已经演变成一个城市中心
with ghettos along its circumference.
[AI] 周边有贫民区。
And in turn. the coherent communities became distinct social groups.
[AI] 反过来。连贯的社区成为不同的社会群体。
alienated from each other and alienated from the place.
[AI] 彼此疏远，与这个地方疏远。
From my point of view.
[AI] 在我看来。
losing the sense of belonging to a place
[AI] 失去对一个地方的归属感
and a sense of sharing it with someone else
[AI] 还有一种与他人分享的感觉
has made it a lot easier to destroy.
[AI] 使它更容易被摧毁。
The clear example can be seen in the informal housing system.
[AI] 非正规住房制度就是一个明显的例子。
which used to host. before the war. over 40 percent of the population.
[AI] 它曾经是主人。战前。超过40%的人口。
Yes. prior to the war. almost half of the Syrian population
[AI] 对战前。几乎一半的叙利亚人口
lived in slums.
[AI] 住在贫民窟。
peripheral areas without proper infrastructure.
[AI] 周边地区没有适当的基础设施。
made of endless rows of bare block boxes
[AI] 由无休止的一排光盒子组成
containing people.
[AI] 包含人。
people who mostly belonged to the same group.
[AI] 大多数属于同一群体的人。
whether based on religion. class. origin or all of the above.
[AI] 是否基于宗教。班来源或以上所有信息。
This ghettoized urbanism proved to be a tangible precursor of war.
[AI] 事实证明，这种贫民区化的都市主义是战争的具体前兆。
Conflict is much easier between pre-categorized areas --
[AI] 预先分类的区域之间的冲突要容易得多--
where the "others" live.
[AI] “其他人”居住的地方。
The ties that used to bind the city together --
[AI] 曾经把城市联系在一起的纽带--
whether they were social. through coherent building.
[AI] 他们是否是社会性的。通过连贯的建设。
or economic. through trade in the souk.
[AI] 或者说是经济上的。通过露天市场的交易。
or religious. through the coexistent presence --
[AI] 或者宗教的。通过共存的存在--
were all lost in the misguided and visionless modernization
[AI] 都迷失在被误导的、没有远见的现代化中
of the built environment.
[AI] 对建筑环境的影响。
Allow me an aside.
[AI] 请允许我旁听一下。
When I read about heterogeneous urbanism in other parts of the world.
[AI] 当我读到世界其他地区的异质城市化时。
involving ethnic neighborhoods in British cities
[AI] 涉及英国城市中的少数民族社区
or around Paris or Brussels.
[AI] 或者巴黎或布鲁塞尔附近。
I recognize the beginning of the kind of instability
[AI] 我认识到这种不稳定的开始
we have witnessed so disastrously here in Syria.
[AI] 我们在叙利亚目睹了如此灾难性的情况。
We have severely destroyed cities.
[AI] 我们严重破坏了城市。
such as Homs. Aleppo. Daraa and many others.
[AI] 比如霍姆斯。阿勒颇。达拉和其他许多人。
and almost half of the population of the country is now displaced.
[AI] 该国近一半的人口现在流离失所。
Hopefully. the war will end.
[AI] 有希望地战争将结束。
and the question that. as an architect. I have to ask. is:
[AI] 问题是。作为一名建筑师。我得问问。是：
How do we rebuild?
[AI] 我们如何重建？
What are the principles that we should adopt
[AI] 我们应该采取什么原则
in order to avoid repeating the same mistakes?
[AI] 为了避免重蹈覆辙？
From my point of view. the main focus should be on creating places
[AI] 在我看来。重点应该放在创造场所上
that make their people feel they belong.
[AI] 这让他们的人民感到他们属于自己。
Architecture and planning need to recapture
[AI] 架构和规划需要重新获得
some of the traditional values that did just that.
[AI] 一些传统价值观正是如此。
creating the conditions for coexistence and peace.
[AI] 为共存与和平创造条件。
values of beauty that don't exhibit ostentation.
[AI] 不炫耀的美的价值观。
but rather. approachability and ease.
[AI] 而是。平易近人和轻松。
moral values that promote generosity and acceptance.
[AI] 促进慷慨和接受的道德价值观。
architecture that is for everyone to enjoy. not just for the elite.
[AI] 让每个人都能享受的建筑。不仅仅是精英。
just as used to be in the shadowed alleys of the old Islamic city.
[AI] 就像过去在伊斯兰古城的阴暗小巷里一样。
mixed designs that encourage a sense of community.
[AI] 鼓励社区意识的混合设计。
There is a neighborhood here in Homs that's called Baba Amr
[AI] 霍姆斯有一个叫Baba Amr的社区
that has been fully destroyed.
[AI] 这已经被完全摧毁。
Almost two years ago. I introduced this design
[AI] 差不多两年前。我介绍了这个设计
into a UN-Habitat competition for rebuilding it.
[AI] 进入联合国人居署的重建竞争。
The idea was to create an urban fabric inspired by a tree.
[AI] 这个想法是以一棵树为灵感，创造一种城市织物。
capable of growing and spreading organically.
[AI] 能够有机地生长和传播。
echoing the traditional bridge hanging over the old alleys.
[AI] 与悬挂在老胡同上的传统桥梁相呼应。
and incorporating apartments. private courtyards. shops.
[AI] 和合并公寓。私人庭院。商店。
workshops. places for parking and playing and leisure.
[AI] 讲习班。停车、玩耍和休闲的地方。
trees and shaded areas.
[AI] 树木和阴影区。
It's far from perfect. obviously.
[AI] 这远非完美。明显地
I drew it during the few hours of electricity we get.
[AI] 我在用电的几个小时里画的。
And there are many possible ways to express belonging and community
[AI] 有很多可能的方式来表达归属感和社区感
through architecture.
[AI] 通过建筑。
But compare it with the freestanding. disconnected blocks
[AI] 但将其与独立式进行比较。断开连接的块
proposed by the official project for rebuilding Baba Amr.
[AI] 由重建Baba Amr的官方项目提出。
Architecture is not the axis around which all human life rotates.
[AI] 建筑不是所有人类生命旋转的轴心。
but it has the power to suggest and even direct human activity.
[AI] 但它有能力建议甚至指导人类活动。
In that sense. settlement. identity and social integration
[AI] 从这个意义上说。协议身份和社会融合
are all the producer and product of effective urbanism.
[AI] 都是有效城市化的生产者和产物。
The coherent urbanism of the old Islamic city
[AI] 旧伊斯兰城市的连贯城市化
and of many old European towns. for instance.
[AI] 还有许多欧洲古老的城镇。例如。
promote integration.
[AI] 促进融合。
while rows of soulless housing or tower blocks.
[AI] 而一排排没有灵魂的房屋或塔楼。
even when they are luxurious.
[AI] 即使它们很豪华。
tend to promote isolation and "otherness."
[AI] 倾向于促进孤立和“差异性”
Even simple things
[AI] 即使是简单的事情
like shaded places or fruit plants or drinking water inside the city
[AI] 比如阴凉的地方或者城市里的水果植物或者饮用水
can make a difference in how people feel towards the place.
[AI] 可以改变人们对这个地方的感觉。
and whether they consider it a generous place that gives.
[AI] 他们是否认为这是一个慷慨的地方。
a place that's worth keeping. contributing to.
[AI] 一个值得保留的地方。有助于。
or whether they see it as an alienating place.
[AI] 或者他们是否认为这是一个疏远的地方。
full of seeds of anger.
[AI] 充满愤怒的种子。
In order for a place to give. its architecture should be giving. too.
[AI] 为了得到一个给予的地方。它的架构应该是给予。也
Our built environment matters.
[AI] 我们的建筑环境很重要。
The fabric of our cities is reflected in the fabric of our souls.
[AI] 我们城市的结构反映在我们灵魂的结构中。
And whether in the shape of informal concrete slums
[AI] 以及是否以非正式的混凝土贫民窟的形式出现
or broken social housing
[AI] 还是破碎的社会住房
or trampled old towns
[AI] 还是被践踏的旧城镇
or forests of skyscrapers.
[AI] 或者摩天大楼林立。
the contemporary urban archetypes
[AI] 当代城市原型
that have emerged all across the Middle East
[AI] 中东各地都出现了这种情况
have been one cause of the alienation and fragmentation of our communities.
[AI] 已经成为我们社区疏远和分裂的原因之一。
We can learn from this.
[AI] 我们可以从中学习。
We can learn how to rebuild in another way.
[AI] 我们可以学习如何以另一种方式重建。
how to create an architecture that doesn't contribute only
[AI] 如何创建一个不只是贡献的架构
to the practical and economic aspects of people's lives.
[AI] 人们生活的实际和经济方面。
but also to their social. spiritual and psychological needs.
[AI] 而且对他们的社会也有影响。精神和心理需求。
Those needs were totally overlooked in the Syrian cities before the war.
[AI] 这些需求在战前的叙利亚城市被完全忽略了。
We need to create again cities that are shared
[AI] 我们需要再次创建共享的城市
by the communities that inhabit them.
[AI] 他们居住的社区。
If we do so. people will not feel the need
[AI] 如果我们这样做。人们不会觉得有必要
to seek identities opposed to the other identities all around.
[AI] 寻找与周围其他身份相反的身份。
because they will all feel at home.
[AI] 因为他们都会有宾至如归的感觉。
Thank you for listening.
[AI] 谢谢你的收听。